We'll be right back.
Hello?
Oh, there we are.
All right.
Good morning, Canvas.
How is everybody doing?
Good.
Those of you who bloom, did you have a good weekend?
Yes.
Those of you who didn't, you're glad you skipped town, but we're glad you're back.
Okay, good.
Got it.
All right.
My name is Jill Keister, and I get the privilege of sharing just a few announcements with you guys this morning.
If this is your first time, we welcome you.
We are so glad that you are here, and we would love to connect with you.
You can use this QR code or fill out the little card in your bulletin that you got at the front door.
We would love to just send you an email.
Just get your information a little bit.
We won't spam you, I promise.
And the welcome desk in the back, there's a small gift for you.
We would love to connect with you in that way as well, so be sure to stop by there.
Club 54.
For our fourth and fifth graders, they are meeting tonight for pizza, games, music, and Jesus.
So if you have a fifth and fourth grader, bring them out tonight.
It is at 6, and pickup is at 7.30.
Be sure to bring their friends.
It's definitely going to be a great time.
This happens every first Sunday of the month.
Also, our youth group, they are going to meet this Wednesday for their Cultivate Hangout night,
so that's exciting.
Youth guys, be sure to bring friends.
That is for sixth through twelfth graders, and that is from sixth to eighth.
They also will have pizza, snacks, a short devotional video.
You do not need to sign up for that.
Just come on out, and again, that's Wednesday, so be sure to do that.
I think I got the wrong...
No, there we go.
Okay, sorry.
My phone went the wrong way.
Abba Care Walk for Life, that is coming up May 16th.
We have a team that has already started to assemble.
If you have any further questions about that, if you'd like to join or donate, you can do
that through the church website or talk to Rachel Sampsel.
Again, that is on the 16th, and it's a great cause if you'd like to support them.
And our last announcement is our missions team is going to be doing their trip to Blazing
Hope in September this year.
Yes, Blazing Hope, that's in Tennessee.
If you'd like more information about that, you can see Mike Gad.
They would love to have you, or you can email him at missions at canvascommunity.church.
We would love to encourage you to give in a way back to the church.
You can do that in the tower in the back, and you can also do that online.
And again, it's so great to see all of you this morning, and we're going to worship.
So let's go ahead and stand and get ready for that.
As the Spirit was moving over the water, Spirit, come move over us.
Come rest over us.
Come rest on us.
Walk down, Spirit, when you move, you make my heart pound.
When you fill the room, you're here, and I know you are moving.
I'm here, and I know you will fill me.
Spirit, when you move, you make my heart pound.
When you fill the room, you're here, and I know you are moving.
I'm here, and I know you will fill me.
When you fill the room, you're here, and I know you are moving over the water, you're here, and I know you are moving over the water.
When you fill the room, you're here, and I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water.
I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water.
I know you are moving over the water, and I know you are moving over the water.
I know you are moving over the water.
I am child of God.
Father, today we come as your children, your sons and your daughters, so grateful that
you have looked down on us in our imperfections and unworthiness and chosen to give us life,
to give us your son and your spirit.
Thank you, Lord, that you're never, we're never apart from you.
For those today that don't, don't trust you, have not submitted their lives to you,
I pray that today they will feel your arms around them.
I pray they will know that your gift is available even to them.
I pray you'll bless Kent as he comes and delivers your word.
Lord, open our hearts and our minds to hear what you have for us today.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Amen.
Well, good morning, Canvas.
I'd like to welcome you to our new four-week series on the book of Jonah.
Jonah is one of those stories in the Bible, like, I don't know, the temptations of Christ
or the prodigal son, that is just so richly written.
It's so many layers there.
We could talk about it every Sunday for months and never repeat ourselves, but we're going
to do it in four weeks.
And like the prodigal son, Jonah is a story about repentance.
And more than that, it's about an obdurate desire to get our own way and resist repentance
and to bring God back our direction instead of us going his way.
And much like the prodigal son, in the first part of the story, our main character rebels
and flees.
And then we see repentance and bitterness in the second half when God forgives those who
repent, which is an unexpected turn.
It's a very unique story.
To get everybody on the same page, the story in brief, it's a very short story, carefully
crafted, but you can read it in a few minutes, the whole book.
Very quickly, a prophet, Jonah, was told by God to go deliver a message to his sworn enemies
that they should repent or they'll be destroyed.
He'd rather they were destroyed, so he doesn't want to deliver the message.
So he runs the other direction, gets on a boat.
God sends a storm.
He's eventually overboard in the storm and swallowed by a fish that spits him back up on shore,
at which point, having had an attitude adjustment, he goes to where God has asked him to go and
delivers the message.
His enemies do repent.
They are forgiven.
And he sits outside the city wishing that they'd been, you know, smitten.
So that's a unique story.
And it's presented in four scenes.
I just told you a lot of action.
But each chapter is kind of a quick scene, the bulk of which is talking, right?
And it's a conversation about or to God.
And so the story is really about those conversations.
In the first chapter, which we're going to look at today in addition to introducing the book,
is a sermon.
While he's in the storm, he talks to the sailors about who God is.
And that's really the core of that story.
In the second chapter, he says a prayer from inside the belly of the fish.
In the third chapter, he finally delivers the message of who God is to his enemies.
And in the fourth chapter, he sits outside the city and talks to God about what's happened.
So it's those conversations, four scenes, four conversations.
That really is what this book is about.
It's just a rich, compact, and really carefully crafted story,
where God reveals his character in stark juxtaposition to a man's character,
a man, unfortunately, like ourselves.
And it shows us who God is and what we look like standing before him.
Which means this is not about a whale, right?
It's not a story about a whale.
It's a short book.
It's 47 verses.
Three of them mention the fish, which means about 6%, which means 94% of the story, not about fish, okay?
So, and also, just for the record, this was not a time when this was written.
There was not in-depth scientific taxonomy.
There were basically two things in the ocean, things you could eat and things that could eat you.
And this was of the second category, right?
In some older translations, it says a sea monster came up.
In some translations, it says a whale because they figured it had to be a whale at some point.
It usually just says fish.
But whatever it was, it was a big, scary thing that could swallow a man, right?
We'll say fish.
The second thing this story is not about, which you may have heard frequently said, is it's not about Jonah hiding from God, right?
It's very important that we recognize that throughout this story, at no point does God ever say, where'd Jonah go, right?
It never happened.
What we read in Psalm 138 this morning, 139, was a psalm that David had written generations before Jonah.
Jonah knew that.
He knew that God would see him in the depths of Sheol and the heights of heaven.
If he got on a boat and went to the far ends of the sea, which is what he did, God would be there, right?
He knew that.
And he expected God to see him.
This is not a story about him trying to hide from God.
This is a story about a man seeking to frustrate God's plans by not taking part in them, okay?
And we'll see more about that.
And oddly, the last thing the story's not about, given that it's a minor prophet, is it's not a book about prophecy, you know?
There is prophecy in it, just like there's a fish in it, but that's not the primary part of the story.
It's not about him delivering the prophecies that he delivered.
It's a story about the prophet and his failure to deliver, as he should.
And to be clear then, what is a prophet in the Old Testament and the Bible at large?
A prophet is, a prophecy isn't something that tells the future, okay?
A prophet is somebody who speaks the word of God.
A priest would speak to God for the people.
A prophet would speak to the people for God, and frequently to the king for God.
And frequently, those messages would have some sort of ultimated in it.
And it told the future in the same way that your mom tells the future when she says, if you don't clean your room, you're going to be grounded for the rest of your life, right?
It's really easy to tell the future when you control the future, right?
And so there would be these, the prophets would frequently come with promised punishment or discipline if the disobedience continued, or promises of faithfulness to a thousand generations, right?
If, in fact, you would be faithful and cease from your disobedience.
So in that sense, prophets would tell the future, but they were there to deliver messages from God.
And their role was that they frequently delivered those messages to the king.
And they often said, who is God saying should be king?
So they were the king makers.
It was an official role.
It was a feared role, and the kings would fear the prophets.
Before they would engage in international relations, they would check with the prophet as to, is this advisable and allowable?
Before they entered war, the prophet would have to sanction it.
So he was, he had a role more like secretary of state or something than like, you know, a guy walking around telling fortunes.
You know, he's not a crystal ball guy.
He's a secretary of state guy, okay?
This particular prophet, Jonah, I would like to position in your mind who he is.
And to do that, I'm going to need to step back in time a little bit, and I crave your indulgence, a very quick bit of history.
Six months ago, when I was standing up here, we talked about a time in Exodus 34 when Moses stood on Mount Sinai and God revealed his character to Moses.
He said, Yahweh, Yahweh, I'm a God merciful and gracious, slow to anger, abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness, keeping steadfast love for thousands of generations, forgiving iniquity and transgressions and sin, but who will by no means clear the guilty.
He said that to Moses in response to the fact that having just told the people of Israel who gathered at the foot of Mount Sinai how they should live their lives around him, how they should worship him as a God who would be their chieftain and leader and live with him.
He was not an idol.
He was a single God.
The Lord your God is one.
And he told them all these things about how to live their entire nation, should live their life around him.
They immediately chose instead to build a golden calf and say, we're going to worship you as if you were an idol, which is the way we understood God's working back in Egypt.
And what we're going to do is we're going to, as if you were a beast that we could harness to drag us where we want to go.
We want to treat you like someone we can propitiate to and manipulate you to give us what we want, right?
And we're going to have a different relationship with you.
We're going to have different festivals and different priests and different kinds of sacrifice so that we can live life in the way that we feel in control of.
There was a reckoning that came from that, and Israel struggled with this transition to worshiping God in the way he directed them and understanding who he was.
But hundreds of years later, finally, King David was born and brought the nation together, brought all the tribes together into a nation that did, in fact, live their lives around the worship of Yahweh as directed to Moses on Mount Sinai, right?
Aaron had said, behold, Aaron was Moses' brother back when the golden calf.
He had declared, behold, these are your gods who brought you out of Egypt.
And there was a struggle against, when he talked about the golden calf, there was a struggle understanding who God really was until David was at last finally able to unify the country around this.
And he made, with his faith in God, he built the nations to great, very large borders, and they were a dominant, influential force in the region.
He passed this powerful country that was centered around God onto his son with the instruction that he should build a temple in the center of their major city so that the country could, in fact, live their lives around God as he instructed Moses on Mount Sinai in Exodus 34.
And Solomon did that.
There's this really excellent moment in 2 Chronicles 6 and 1 Kings 8 where Solomon is dedicating the temple to God.
And he prays a prayer that really you should read over and over.
It's a fantastic prayer.
It's recorded in the Bible multiple times.
But a key part of it, he says, Lord God, when we sin and when we do receive the punishment that you told us about on Mount Sinai, when you don't let evil go unpunished, even though you're gracious to thousands of generations.
So when that happens and when we're conquered and when we're sold into slavery and when bad things happen in battle, please allow us to turn back and face you at this temple and pray to you and you restore us when we turn and repent.
Right?
That was the prayer.
And in 2 Chronicles 7, 14, the Lord replies to him, if my people who are called by my name will humble themselves and pray and seek my face and turn from their wicked ways, then I will hear from heaven.
Not the temple.
I'm everywhere.
You can take the wings of the morning, go to the end of the ocean, and I'm there.
Right?
I will hear from heaven and will redeem your land.
I will heal you.
I will have you back.
You will be forgiven if you repent, just like I promised Moses.
Right?
So this is the nation that was built.
And unfortunately, when Solomon passed away, the wealth and power of the kingdom was too enticing to his heirs.
And they split the kingdom in half.
The northern kingdom that kept the name of Israel.
The southern kingdom that kept the temple and called itself Judah.
The king of the northern kingdom, Jeroboam, did not want his people going to the southern kingdom to worship God.
And to be, God had given him this temple so they would be unified around him.
Jeroboam now wants them to be divided and to stay and honor his power.
And so what he did in what would forever and more be known in the Bible as the sin of Jeroboam,
in 2 Kings 14, I'm sorry, 1 Kings 12, he built two golden calves, put one on the northern and southern border,
so he never had to leave his kingdom to worship God the way they decided.
And he said, this, O Israel, is your God who brought you up out of Egypt.
And reinstantiated the idolatry that was set up at Mount Sinai that God had spoken out against.
And so the northern kingdom from then on out was in this syncretistic worship where they claimed to worship Yahweh.
And they had the Old Testament, you know, prophecies that we have today.
And they heard from God.
But they worshipped him in the way that would further their desires for their kingdom, not his creation.
And they came to those golden calves and worshipped them with their own feast festival,
their own feast schedule and their own festivals and their own kind of sacrifice.
About 150 years into that kingdom, his descendant, Jeroboam II, came to power and he brought Israel to its greatest grandeur.
Jeroboam's goal was to make Israel great again.
He wanted to reach back and take the virtues of the kingdom of Solomon and use them synthetically
to expand Israel's self-image and boundaries until they were as rich and as grand as Solomon had ever made them.
Not understanding that God had made them that way.
And he wanted to do that by harnessing the golden calves and the idol worship and keeping people in his kingdom focused on him and his goals.
And he had a prophet that was with him who prophesied that God would, in fact,
aid him in expanding his kingdoms, that he would build the great kingdom.
And that prophet's name was Jonah.
Jonah was Jeroboam's prophet who led his people in the worship of the golden calves,
away from centering their lives around Yahweh and the way they'd been instructed.
As Jeroboam expanded his kingdom for his own glory.
Okay?
That's who Jonah was.
And everybody who read this story back then would have known that.
When we read the opening lines, which we're going to read now.
Now the word of the Lord came to Jonah, son of Amittai.
Everybody instantly knows who that is, right?
That's the secretary of state of the northern kingdom, right?
The Lord of the Lord came to Jonah, son of Amittai, saying,
Arise, go to Nineveh, the great city, and call out against it.
For their evil has come up before me.
And he used that phrase all throughout the Old Testament when someone was murdered,
and just the stench of evil coming up, right?
Has come up before me.
But Jonah rose and fled to Tarshish, away from the presence of the Lord.
And he went down to Joppa and found a ship going to Tarshish.
And he paid the fare and went down into it to go with them to Tarshish,
away from the presence of the Lord.
And the Lord hurled a great wind upon the sea.
And there was a mighty tempest on the sea.
And the ship threatened to break up.
And then the mariners were afraid.
And each one cried out to his own God.
And they hurled the cargo that was in the ship into the sea to lighten it for them.
But Jonah had gone down into the innermost bowels of the ship
and had lain down and was fast asleep.
So the captain came to him and said,
What do you mean, you sleeper?
Arise, call out to your God.
Perhaps the God will give a thought to us so that we may not perish.
And they said to one another,
Come, let's cast lots, which is rolling dice or drawing straws or something.
Cast lots so that we may know on whose account this evil has come upon us.
So they cast lots and the lot fell on Jonah.
And then they said to him,
Tell us on whose account this evil has come upon us.
What's your occupation?
Where do you come from?
What's your country?
Of what people are you?
And he said to them,
I am a Hebrew,
which was a term that the outsiders used speaking of them.
So he's speaking to foreigners.
I am a Hebrew,
and I fear the Lord God of heaven,
who made the sea and the dry land.
And then the men were exceedingly afraid.
And they said to them,
What is this you've done?
For the men knew that he was fleeing from the presence of the Lord,
because he told them.
And then they said to him,
What shall we do to you that the sea may quiet down for us?
For the sea had grown more and more tempestuous.
And he said to them,
Pick me up and hurl me into the sea,
and the sea will quiet down for you.
For I know it's because of me that this great tempest has come upon you.
Nevertheless,
the men rode hard to try to get back to land,
but they could not,
for the sea grew more and more tempestuous against them.
And therefore they called out to the Lord,
O Lord,
let us not perish for this man's life,
and lay not on us his innocent blood.
For you,
O Lord,
have done as it pleased you.
So they picked Jonah up and hurled him into the sea,
and the sea ceased from its raging.
And then the men feared the Lord exceedingly.
And they offered a sacrifice to the Lord,
and they made vows.
And the Lord appointed a great fish to swallow up Jonah.
And Jonah was in the belly of the fish for three days and three nights.
That is a well-told tale,
and it is a story about repentance and rebellion.
Repentance,
because maybe more than any other story in the Bible,
this literally,
physically is a picture of someone fleeing from the will of God,
needing to turn and come back to God.
It's a physical picture of repentance and the failure to do it.
It's about rebellion,
because Jonah thinks,
God can't make me do it,
right?
I'll just get in a boat and go the other way.
You can't stop my boat.
And God's like,
well,
God can,
you know.
Are you sure?
And he's like,
well,
then I'll just drown.
And God says,
are you sure?
You know?
And so he believes that he's going to keep rebelling.
And the key thing,
this is so well told,
there's many literary devices.
We're just going to focus on a few.
One is that everything is so deliberately out of place,
the way the author writes it.
We have a prophet of God defying God.
That ain't normal.
We have a man deliberately fleeing into danger because he wants the danger,
right?
That's not normal.
His priorities in life have gotten twisted,
right?
We have him,
yes,
surviving,
being ingested by a fish,
right?
That's not normal.
Everything's just sort of out of place.
And it would have been just as odd to them then as it is now.
Maybe more odd to them because they've got a lot more implications of this without hearing it explained.
And the motif of the sea that we must understand that they would have heard is everyone understood the sea to be the primordial chaos that was out to get them,
out of which God had brought forth the good world when he created it.
Like God had raised the good clean land that they could live on out of the primordial chaos of the sea,
which like in the times of Noah was always ready to come sweep them away,
right?
And so there's always a fear of the sea and of what's down at the bottom,
which is death and shield.
When they say shield,
it's down at the bottom of the primordial chaos.
And there's frequently throughout the Old Testament,
the messenger of God will experience and exhibit the power of God by overcoming the power of the sea,
the primordial chaos,
right?
Think about Moses coming through the Red Sea,
for instance.
There's many examples,
Noah being an obvious one.
And in Revelation,
when it says there'll be a time with no more sea,
the land,
the creation is fully built and there's no more primordial chaos.
That's the image,
right?
But Jonah wants to be chucked into it,
He's trying to get away from God's good creation.
And so we see these rapid movements.
The story's told in a really rapid fire style that exists in Hebrew that allows you to run through a story
till you get to the important part that you want people to focus on.
And in that bit,
it says he goes down to the sea and down into the bottom of the boat,
as close to Sheol as he can,
and then down into the water.
And then the great fish takes him down.
And the image of being in the fish's belly is that he's being dragged down to Sheol,
right?
It's the image of a living death.
And so that rapid fire narrative is rushing us through till we can get to them talking.
And you'll just have to take my word for this.
This first chapter is carefully structured in rings around a central core statement.
And that core statement is,
I serve the Lord God of heaven who made the sea and the dry land.
You would think the central part would be,
I'm running away from God,
but the author has carefully crafted it so that that's sort of said as an after statement.
Because while that's important to the story,
it's not the key thing that's going on in the world,
right?
Jonah fears the Lord God of heaven who made the sea and the dry land.
And when the author says that,
he's having Jonah quote Scripture.
He's quoting,
he's referencing Psalm 95.
For the Lord is great God and great King above all gods.
In his hands are the depths of the earth,
and the heights of the mountains are also his,
and the sea is his,
for he made it,
for he formed the dry land.
Today,
if you hear my voice,
don't harden your hearts as you did in the wilderness.
This is referencing a psalm that Jonah knows,
which is referencing what happened just after,
when they're out in the desert and they harden their hearts and wouldn't follow God,
right?
He is the God who's with you everywhere of the sea and the dry land.
And Jonah's saying,
I know he's in control.
I know I shouldn't harden my heart and rebel against him.
But oh,
by the way,
I'm fleeing from his face,
right?
Everything in this story is obeying God.
The sea does what he wants.
The winds,
he hurls the winds.
The boat,
the language in Hebrew,
the boat has almost thoughts.
It's thinking about breaking up,
but it's holding it together because he's supposed to,
right?
Everybody's obeying God,
including the pagan fishermen,
right?
Who fear the Lord and are trying really hard not to kill this guy,
Except for Jonah.
And we should notice that the prophet comes through the waters as a hero of the Old Testament
should,
and is willing to give his life and intercession for others.
But he's doing it selfishly this time.
He's not actually caring about them.
God has told him,
go to the great city whose evil has come up before me,
referencing all the murder of the Old Testament when he says that phrase.
And Jonah could go out and try to save those people,
but he is not interested.
He's not here to save anybody who's not from Israel,
right?
He should have been prophesying to repentance to his nation who was living in pagan idolatry.
And God has sent him to see another nation who is also living in pagan idolatry,
surely hoping he'll notice the similarity,
and that when they repent,
this will be a message that he can bring back to his people.
But Jonah wants no part of it.
He's sent to Nineveh.
Incidentally,
Nineveh is modern-day Mosul in Iraq.
So throw the map up there for a minute.
So it would become, though,
the capital of Assyria.
God sends him,
asks him to go 750 miles northeast to what's now Mosul.
Instead, he gets on a boat.
He goes down, down, down.
Gets on a boat and travels 3,000 miles west.
Or tries to.
He goes through the Straits of Gibraltar,
out into the Atlantic,
to the far side of Spain,
right?
That's where he wants to get to.
As far as he knows,
that's where all the maps of the world end.
He's literally going out into the primordial chaos.
And he's doing this to get away from the major city of Nineveh.
It's not the capital yet.
It will become the capital.
But it's like the New York City of Assyria.
And it's populated by a violent, brutal enemy.
Nahum later will describe some of their acts,
if you want to go read it,
or if you just want to even look at their art.
The artwork of the Assyrians
shows, you know,
mutilated and flayed enemies
because what they wanted to do
was spread terror around to anybody who wasn't them.
They were what Jeroboam was trying to make Israel.
God was trying to make them repent
as he had told Israel to do.
They were all fleeing the wrong direction.
And Jonah, therefore,
had very real reason to hate and fear them.
These two violent cultures
that were trying to be the dominant,
country in this region.
They couldn't both exist.
They knew there was a reckoning coming.
And it was the undoing of Jonah's life work
to try to save these people.
God points out that there's great evil
and he wants to restore his creation.
He wants to correct it.
Jonah wants only to restore his nation.
Plus, it would have been very unsettling
both to Jeroboam
and to Shalmaneser, capital of Assyria,
if, you know,
Jonah had walked into his country
and started telling them how to behave
to obey his God
so that they would be saved.
I don't think either king
would be excited about that, right?
It would have been dangerous for Jonah.
It would have been the end of his career, right?
It's a very difficult thing
he's being asked to do
independent of all the rest of this story.
And so we see in the end
that Jonah basically believed three things.
He believed in the absolute sovereignty of God.
He believed that repentance would occur
if God sent him on this mission
and that God would forgive these people.
He says that clearly.
He also believes in the conservation of mass.
He believes if he's not in Assyria,
if he's on his way to Tarshish,
he can't be in Assyria
and therefore he can't help, right?
He thinks he can foil the plan
by not being there.
And the third thing he believes
is that he is not gonna help Assyria.
He's just not gonna do it
because he knows exactly who God is.
If we're not sure about it in chapter one,
by chapter four, he says to God,
I knew that you're a gracious and compassionate God,
slow to anger, abundant in mercy,
one who relents from disaster.
He's quoting God from Exodus 34
where he says who he is.
He understands his place in his story.
And he says, I knew you were that God
and because I've joined in your effort
to save the Ninevites,
it's better that I should die
than that I should live, right?
So he ran saying, if I'm absent, I can't help.
If I die, I'll remain absent
because he never doubted that if they repented,
God would forgive them.
And mostly then this is about his refusal to prophesy.
And incidentally, when he does prophesy,
he famously says as few words as possible.
He just runs into the city and says,
you're all gonna die.
You know, it's, he only says five words.
He's the worst prophet on record.
And God still uses it.
Nineveh still repents.
Just like in chapter one,
he says to the men on the ship,
yep, you know, I'm running from God.
He controls the world.
I guess you're gonna have to murder me.
You know, and somehow that saves them.
They turn to God.
They make vows and build a sacrifice
and come to fear God
because God can show his power
independent of how badly we do our jobs, okay?
Not that you should try to do your job badly.
The moral of the story is not to copy Jonah,
but one thing, one question remains then
is did Jonah ever repent?
Was he like too far gone?
And did Nineveh ever fully repent?
It seems they did.
They went back on it in a few generations.
And if you wanna read Nahum
and see what happened next, you may.
But we have to realize that at least in part,
this story had to have been self-reported.
Nobody but Jonah and God
were there in chapter two and chapter four, right?
So the only way we can know about that
is if Jonah told somebody.
So that gives us hope.
As Tim Keller actually said,
Jonah must have realized
he was as wicked as the Ninevites
and that he too was living only by the mercy of God.
And so this book is Jonah's confession
of his shortcomings,
which gives us hope that he may have gone back
and tried to persuade Israel to repent.
But for what we know in chapter one,
he runs down, down, down,
away from the presence of God
into the chaos of the sea.
As we saw on the map,
3,000 miles the other way to Tarshish.
And Tarshish, by the way,
is three things in this story.
The people that are reading it
would have immediately recognized.
One, it's not Nineveh, right?
He's trying to stay away from Nineveh.
Number two, it's the ends of the earth
like we saw on the map, right?
It's as far off the map as you can get.
Nothing past that is charted.
And third thing,
it's the place where Solomon had gone
to get all his riches and jewels
and the things that he used to build his kingdom,
to make it grating.
And Jonah's still in his mind.
I mean, we didn't go down on a royal barge.
Jeroboam didn't send him.
He bought a ticket on a passing fisherman ship.
But he's going to the place
where he might be able to find the strength
to build the kingdom on his own, right?
He thinks he can control his location on the planet.
But in doing that,
he's assuming he can harness God's creation
to thwart God's will,
which is a serious mistake.
God hurls the wind at him and blows him back.
The pagan sailors, on the other hand,
they fear God more than the prophet does.
And they begin to,
they're so upset by the storm,
they're panicking and they're acting in unsailerly ways.
They throw their life,
you know, all their money that's invested in his voyage,
they throw it overboard.
So they're destitute
and probably going to be sold to slaves when they get back.
That's how bad the storm is.
They're willing to risk that, right?
They're trying to row in the storm
to save Jonah's life, which is absurd.
You can't row in a storm.
You're going to lose or break your oars.
Everyone knows it's not,
but they're just trying everything they can
because they're resisting shedding innocent blood.
This will be echoed later in the New Testament
as Pilate, another Gentile,
sent to put on a collision course
with a messenger of God who's about to be killed,
washes his hands and said,
the blood of this innocent man is not on me.
And in the bottom of the boat,
while all this chaos is going on,
Jonah is asleep.
Why on earth is that?
And more importantly,
where else in the Bible do we see another person
sleeping in a boat in the storm?
Ah, Jesus, right, Mark 4, right?
Again, we see both Jonah and Jesus
in a boat with professional fishermen
who are out of their depths
and afraid they're going to die
and their skills are up to no avail
in the great power of the primordial chaos
and the storm that God is in control of,
but they don't know that
or they're forgetting their panic.
And in both cases,
Jonah and Jesus can sleep through it
because they have an absolute assurance
in God's mission to provide salvation
to all nations and their place in it.
They have zero fear of death.
Jesus, because he knows his time has not yet come.
Jonah, because he's kind of hoping it has, right?
He just wants out.
Jesus gets up and calms the storm
out of compassion for his shipmates.
And the sailors in both situations
are just suddenly in awe of the power
that can stop a storm.
And it is a conversion moment for both of them.
They turn and begin the path of repentance
to face back toward God's face
and seek his face
and turn from their pagan ways.
Jonah, at some point,
could have jumped out of the boat himself.
I don't know if you've thought about that.
He could have said,
I'm going to save these guys.
But he's not
because it's a sin to commit suicide, right?
He's trying to stay technically
on the right side of God
while he flees from his face, right?
He didn't give a toss about his shipmates.
He's more concerned, it would seem,
about technically not sinning.
And the sailors, on the other hand,
are trying everything they can to save Jonah.
But ultimately, it comes to the point
where separating from Jonah
becomes the only solution for them.
And so,
the appointed messenger of God
is handed over to Gentiles
to absorb the consequences of rebellion
so that others might live.
God allows the Gentiles
to distance themselves from his wrath
by placing his wrath on his chosen messenger
who becomes,
with his life,
the instrument of their salvation.
And incidentally,
another parallels years later
in the port city of Joppa
where Jonah found this boat,
the only time Joppa is mentioned
in the New Testament.
Simon Peter will be sent on a mission.
Simon, son of Jonah, he's called,
both because his father's name is Jonah
and because he is carrying on the mission
that Jonah has here in imagery.
He's sent out from Joppa as a messenger
to the violent, invading,
brutal, Gentile nation of his day,
which was Rome.
So, everything in the story
is moving toward that idea
that God is the God of all nations
and wants the Gentiles to repent
and wants the prophet to turn
from his prideful ways
and help him get the whole world
to be restored.
Lose sight of your nation
and look at my creation.
Everything in this story
is about repentance
and about God providing a path
back to himself
for all nations,
even the unrighteous,
oppressive foreigners
that you hate.
And often we, like Jonah,
are not quite as righteous
as we believe.
We obey in the ways
that make sense to us
and we flee from God
in the areas
that don't seem to fit
our self-interest.
When we're asked
to spread his grace
against our self-interest,
a spirit of Jonah
kind of rises up in us.
We can see the sailors,
the pagans,
they're honest
in their recognition
and in their deep gratitude
for God's intervention
in verse 10 and 16.
And we see
that as Jonah knew,
Nineveh is going to embody
this repentance,
which explains
why Jonah is so important
in the New Testament.
Indirectly,
the gospel writers
reference it a lot.
I've mentioned Peter and Joppa,
Pilate washing his hands,
don't let hold me guilty
of the blood
of this innocent man,
Jesus calming the storm
and sleeping in the boat.
There's many more,
but directly,
Jesus himself points out
to his critics
in Matthew 24,
the sign of Jonah,
which, let's read that,
I'm sorry, Matthew 12.
Then some of the scribes
and Pharisees
answered Jesus
and said,
Teacher,
we wish to see
a sign from you.
A sign would be
a miraculous evidence
of his power
that makes them believe
that the authority
he's claiming
is really there.
Okay?
We want a sign from you.
But he answers them,
an evil and adulterous
generation seeks
for a sign.
An evil and adulterous
generation very aptly
describes Israel
at the time of Jonah.
And in this statement,
Jesus is going to apply
that comparison strongly
to the people
standing in front of him.
You ask for a sign,
but no sign will be given you
except the sign
of the prophet Jonah.
For just as Jonah
was three days and nights
in the belly
of the great fish,
so the Son of Man
will be three days
and three nights
in the heart of the earth.
And the men of Nineveh
will rise up in judgment
with this generation,
meaning the people of Judah
standing before him
at the time,
rise up in judgment
of this generation
and condemn it.
For they,
the Ninevites,
repented at the preaching
of Jonah,
and behold,
something greater than Jonah
is here,
Christ himself.
Three days and three nights
in the depths
being dragged down
to Sheol
in the belly of the fish
is a picture of death itself.
And it sounds like in this
that Christ might be saying,
well, okay,
I'm only going to give you
one sign though.
You know,
I'm stingy with my signs.
We know that Christ,
there's many points
with John the Baptist,
with the lame man.
There's many times
when Christ gave a sign
to help people believe
when it was pertinent
and real.
But what he's saying
to these guys
is there's only one sign.
It is an ultimate sign.
There's no other sign you need,
but I'm going to come back
from the dead.
And after three days
was in Jewish understanding
the time when rebirth
was no longer possible.
The spirit had left the body
and he's like,
I'm going to be gone
three days just like Jonah
and then I'll come back
from the dead.
That ought to be
sign enough for you.
And we know from Romans
and from the John,
from the various letters
of the apostles,
this was the sign
that finally and permanently
persuaded them
that he was the Son of God
raised from dead
with power, right?
But the people
that he's speaking to
at this point
want more than a sign.
They want the,
and so he's telling them
just watch,
I'll give you the ultimate sign.
But more than that,
that's not the full sign
of Jonah.
The sign of Jonah,
as he pointed out
in this passage,
is the full miraculous
arc of repentance
and forgiveness
that follows
from the return
from death
and which gives all nations
a path of reconciliation
back to their creator.
The sign of Jonah
is a promise
that despite the obdurate
defiance of my prophets
who would seek to twist
and limit their relationship
with me
to their own purposes,
to the furtherance
of their own power
and their own national ends,
I have the power
over life and death.
I am the God
who made the sea
and the sky
and I have provided
a path back to me
for all people
including your violent
political national enemies,
anyone who will humble themselves
and repent
and seek my face
and will be saved.
So Christ brings this
as a warning
to the citizens of Jerusalem
in his time,
the descendants
of the remnants of Judah
who gathered the Scriptures together
and preserved the story
of Jonah for us.
Judea,
he's pointing out,
is following on the same path
as Jeroboam and Israel
because they're harnessing,
he wants his listeners
to repent
from harnessing,
attempting to harness God
to drag their nation
to the place they want it
to be for their own purposes.
They want to make their nation
great again their way
for their reasons
and they want God
to be their confederate in this.
What he's telling them to do
is to repent
and seek his face
and he'll take care of the nation.
Just live your life around me.
Judea is following
the same path
as Jeroboam the second.
They need to repent
and return from their wicked ways.
Jesus was sent
as promised to Abraham
so that through him
all nations would be blessed.
He is the appointed messenger
of God
handed over to the Gentiles
to absorb the consequences
of rebellion
so that others might live.
God allows the Gentiles
to distance themselves
from his wrath
by placing his wrath
on his chosen messenger
who becomes with his life
the instrument
of their salvation.
And so this story of Jonah
stands in the Old Testament
as a clear and early ethos
of what we tend to think
of as New Testament ethos.
If your enemy is hungry
feed him.
Love your enemies.
Go the extra mile
for your enemy
and that specifically means
go the extra mile
for your soldier
the soldier of your occupying
persecuting
pagan militarized enemy.
Because God is the God
of all nations
he will forgive
for a thousand generations
though he doesn't
love the guilty
to go unpunished.
The story of Jonah
was preserved for us
as a moral lodestar
declaring that God's people
must recognize
this justice
and this mercy
to those who will turn
seek his face
turn from their wicked ways.
And history proves his point.
Within a generation
everything that Jonah feared
came true.
He was right.
His nation did not repent
and the fleeting glory
of Jeroboam
his expansion of Israel
everything that Jonah
was working so hard
against God to preserve
was utterly
and permanently destroyed
by the Assyrians.
Tiglath-Pilesia
rose up with a mighty army
and just wiped Israel
off the map.
But that did not happen
because Nineveh
repented.
That happened
because Israel
didn't repent.
And who was the prophet
who was sent
to make Israel
repent
and to hear
the word of God?
Jonah.
Where did he see
that a violent nation
could repent
and come back to God?
In Nineveh.
But he wouldn't
follow the sign.
They were destroyed
not because of
Nineveh's repentance
but because of Israel's.
Jonah's failure
as a prophet
was failing to focus
his people
on God's character
and his commands.
They did not repent
of their idolatry
the golden calves
the idols they believed
they could harness
like a beast
to pull their nation
to new greatness.
What we see in Jonah
is that God
will never force us
to surrender
to his will.
He'll give us
a lot of reasons
we wish we had.
He'll not force us
any more than
he forced Jonah
or Israel
or Nineveh
or Rome.
He is patient
and gracious
and willing to forgive
but repentance
is not optional.
So to close out
today Ryan
is going to come up
and lead us
through a liturgy
on repentance
and as he does that
what I would like us
to do is all
quietly consider
where we are
willfully refusing
to surrender
parts of our life
to the direction
God has.
well hopefully
you guys
were as challenged
as me
if not
I guess
I have a lot
of repenting
to do.
we are going
to end
by taking
communion
and also
joining together
in a litany
of repentance
a historic
liturgical
prayer of repentance
because
you know
often times
we know
what we need
to do
but we don't
have the language
to do it
and so
a gift
of the historical
church
is to write
down
prayers
for us
so that
when we know
what we need
to do
but we don't
have the words
to do it
we can
and as
Kent shared
there was a few
things on my mind
that I think
are pretty evident
to me
from Kent's
sermon
from the book
of Jonah
and just the irony
that is so obvious
to everyone
except for Jonah
and how often
is that true
of us
how often
are we acting
in ways
that are incongruent
with what
we say
is true
about ourselves
and we
are really
we really
easily see
the irony
in other
people's lives
but when it
comes to
our own
lives
we can
justify
and make
decisions
that are
totally
incongruent
with the
person
that we
say we
are
Jonah
knows
that God
is eager
to forgive
and we
are so eager
to justify
our own
sinful actions
and become
obsessed
with the
sinful actions
of others
and I think
the key
to correcting
that is
repentance
because if we
become a
people who
don't confess
our sins
who don't
repent
we will
very easily
look at
other people's
sin
it will be
very evident
to us
because
we will be
ignorant
of our own
sin
this is why
the Lord's
prayer tells us
every day
confess your
sins
and so
I'd love
for you to
stand with me
I think we
have some
slides
I gave you
guys more
guys a bigger
part than I
normally give
you so I'm
gonna need
your help
you're gonna
have to pay
attention
follow the
slides
and if
these words
resonate with
you I'd love
to invite you
to pray
these words
of repentance
on behalf
of all of
us before
God
most holy
and merciful
Father we
confess to
you and
to one
another that
we have
sinned by
our own
fault
in thought
word
and deed
we have
not loved
you with
our whole
heart
mind
and strength
we have
not loved
our neighbor
as ourselves
have mercy
on us
Lord
we have
been deaf
to your
call to
serve as
Christ
served us
we have
not been
true to
the mind
of Christ
have mercy
on us
Lord
we confess
to you
Lord all
our past
unfaithfulness
the pride
hypocrisy
and impatience
of our
lives
we confess
to you
Lord
our anger
at our
own
frustration
and our
envy of
those more
fortunate than
ourselves
we confess
to you
Lord
our
negligence
and prayer
and worship
and our
failure to
commend the
faith that
is in us
we confess
to you
Lord
accept our
repentance
Lord
for the
wrongs
we have
done
for our
blindness
to human
need
and suffering
and our
indifference
to injustice
and cruelty
accept our
repentance
Lord
accept our
repentance
Lord
for our
waste
and pollution
of your
creation
and our
lack of
concern
for those
who come
after us
accept our
repentance
Lord
restore us
good Lord
and let
your anger
depart from
us
by the cross
and passion
of your
son
our
Lord
bring us
with all
your saints
to the joy
of his
resurrection
almighty
God
the father
of our
Lord
Jesus
Christ
who
desires
not the
death
of sinners
but rather
that they
may turn
from their
wickedness
and live
he pardons
and absolves
all those
who are
truly repentant
and with
sincere heart
believe
in his
holy gospel
therefore
we beseech
you to
grant us
true repentance
by your
Holy Spirit
that those
things may
please you
which we do
in this
day
and that
the rest
of our
lives
may be
pure
and holy
so that
at the
last we
may come
to your
eternal
joy
through
Jesus
Christ
our
Lord
communion
the bread
the cup
the body
of Christ
the blood
of Jesus
is
both
a
ongoing
reminder
that we
need to
repent
that
the cost
of our
sin
is the
death
of the
innocent
son
of God
and it
is also
a reminder
that we
serve a
God
who is
eager
to forgive
who loves
the world
so much
that he
gave his
one
and only
son
so as we
have
repented
if you
have
trusted
in the
Lord
Jesus
I invite
you to
take
his body
broken
for you
Christ's
blood
shed
for you
Father we
thank you
for the
irony
of the
story
of
Jonah
and
we
acknowledge
that
we
often
have
irony
in
our
own
lives
there's
inconsistency
in this
room
there's
inconsistency
in my
own
heart
and we
are
thankful
for the
story
of
Jonah
that
reminds
us
that
you
will
accomplish
your
purposes
whether
we
participate
in
them
or
not
and
Lord
as
those
who
fear
the
one
who
created
land
we
want
to
be
active
participants
in
what
you're
doing
even
though
often
our
wants
fall
short
of
our
actions
and so
by your
Holy
Spirit
empower
us
your
people
to
surrender
to our
own
desires
and to
follow
you
with our
hearts
soul
mind
and
strength
and God
to love
our
neighbor
as
ourselves
the
neighbor
who
doesn't
look like
us
or talk
like
us
the
neighbor
who
believes
different
things
about
the
world
than
we
believe
the
neighbor
who
is
vehemently
opposed
to
your
gospel
the
neighbor
that
most
resembles
the
nation
of
Nineveh
God
bring
those
people
into
our
minds
and
by
your
Holy
Spirit
give
us
your
love
for
them
remove
the
arrogance
and
pride
that
make
us
think
we
are
better
or
more
deserving
of
your
grace
than
others
pray
all of
this
in
Jesus
name
amen
should
be
volunteers
over
here
to
pray
if
there's
something
you
need
prayer
for
or
want
to
talk
through
if
not
you
are
dismissed
go
in
church
go
in
peace
church
and